<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A late great shipwrack of faith occasioned by a fearful wrack of conscience discovered in a sermon preached at Pauls the first day of July, 1655 / by Dan. Cawdrey.</title>
            <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23918</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07922489</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07922489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31442)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1201:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A late great shipwrack of faith occasioned by a fearful wrack of conscience discovered in a sermon preached at Pauls the first day of July, 1655 / by Dan. Cawdrey.</title>
                  <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Crawford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, I, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40475:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40475:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A late Great Shipwrack OF FAITH: Occaſioned by a fearful VVrack of Conſcience. Diſcovered in a SERMON Preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> the firſt day of <hi>July,</hi> 1655.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Dan. Cawdrey</hi> Preacher of the Word, at Great <hi>Billing</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Tim. 3.9.</hi>
                  </bibl> Holding the myſtery of the Faith in a pure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Tim. 4.1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <hi>1.</hi> Now the Spirit ſpeaketh expreſly, that in the latter times, ſome ſhall depart from the Faith, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and unto doctrines of divels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Speaking lies in hypocriſie, having their conſcience ſeared with an hot iron.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Pack Maior. <hi>Tueſday the third day of</hi> July 1655.</p>
            <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dered that Mr. <hi>Daniel Cawdry</hi> be deſired from this Court, to print his Sermon at <hi>Pauls</hi> the laſt Lords day. <hi>Sadler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Cranford,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Phoenix</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40475:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40475:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>CHRISTOPHER PACK.</hi> Lord Major; and to the Honourable Court of Aldermen, of the Famous City of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOURABLE.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing at your request (which was to me little leſse then a command) prevailed with, to tender my ſervice and paines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you at <hi>Pauls,</hi> I began firſt to thinke, that this <hi>unexpected Providence</hi> of God, had ſome intention for <hi>good</hi> to be done; And then to conſider with my ſelf, not what might be moſt <hi>pleaſing,</hi> to ſcratch an <hi>itching eare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> but what <hi>Doctrine</hi> might be moſt <hi>ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> to the time and place, and moſt uſefull and profitable for that great <hi>Panegyris,</hi> or Solemne Aſsembly. And I could pitch upon nothing, (in ſo ſhort a warning) that might (as I conceived) be more <hi>beneficiall,</hi> then this preſent <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> (now humbly preſented to your <hi>Eyes,</hi> as then to your <hi>Eares</hi>) concerning the <hi>ſad,</hi> and never e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough lamented <hi>Shipwrack of the Faith,</hi> amongst ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profeſſours of the Goſpel: my aime being, if not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the <hi>fallen</hi> (who Adder-like refuſe to hear us) yet, by Gods bleſsing, to prevent the fall of others. And truly, had it not been clearly <hi>forepropheſied</hi> of theſe laſt and worst Times, that many ſhould depart from the Faith,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1. 2 Tim. 3.1. 2 Pet. 2.1.3.3,</note> we ſhould have <hi>wondred</hi> the more, to finde this Apostacie, after ſo much light of the Goſpel, ſo long enjoyed; and after
<pb facs="tcp:40475:3"/> ſo ſerious and ſtrict <hi>profeſſion</hi> of it by many, even to <hi>ſuffering</hi> much for it; Not only the truely <hi>Religious</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Land, who ſtand faſt in their old <hi>Integritie,</hi> do wonder at the monſtrous and blaſphemous Opinions, now lately hatched amongſt us, by the power of Hell, and <hi>Prince</hi> of darkeneſse (aſſiſted by thoſe <hi>Locuſts,</hi> the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi>) that craule amongſt us) under the notion of <hi>New lights;</hi> But the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world do ſtand amazed at it: yea ſome <hi>reproach</hi> and deride us, as if <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> (the late ſinke of all Religions) were now removed into England. The <hi>Conjectures</hi> of men, at the cauſes hereof, are almoſt as various, as themſelves. Severall Heads ſeeke out, and have found Several Reaſons of this <hi>Apoſtacie:</hi> We will hear what they ſay.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Some (the <hi>Prelaticall</hi> partie) charge it upon the <hi>Abandoning</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> Goverment, which with a watchfull eye, and ſtrict hand, did Suppreſse, and keep them under. For that, I have theſe things to ſay. <hi>1.</hi> They, the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> did indeed ſuppreſs all ſects (as they called them) that were oppoſite to their <hi>Hierarchicall</hi> Pompe, and Tyranie, but tolerated (yea countenanced) many <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Superſtitions,</hi> and much <hi>Romiſh</hi> and <hi>Arminian Doctrine;</hi> which now ſome <hi>great ones</hi> of their own, and moſt of the preſent <hi>Sectaries,</hi> do openly Preach and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. It is obſervable, that many points of <hi>Poperie,</hi> and <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> are now vented by theſe ſeverall Sects; I know not, to what to impute it, but either to the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Subtletie, who profeſse and Act every Sect; or to the <hi>ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe</hi> of many of thoſe errours, to corrupt nature; that even ignorant and unlearned men, fall into them without any <hi>Teachers;</hi> as well as ſome <hi>Learned Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies;</hi> I wiſh, they would conſider it. <hi>2.</hi> We may truly ſay of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſome of them, they hatcht and bred
<pb facs="tcp:40475:3"/> thoſe <hi>Sects</hi> and Hereſies, which we now labour under: They, by their rigour, in exacting <hi>Conformity,</hi> to need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> firſt drave many to <hi>Seperation,</hi> and then to fall from one errour to another; which now ſhew themſelves, in this time of <hi>Anarchicall</hi> Liberty. <hi>3.</hi> It is indeed want of Government ſetled in the Church, which is the <hi>Inlet</hi> to all theſe errours, and Hereſies; Here was the beginning of our <hi>miſery,</hi> that ſome were haſty to pull down one Government, but had no <hi>minde</hi> to ſet up another; and ſo left the Church, as a <hi>Vineyard</hi> without hedge or Wall, to be trampled down and eaten up by all the Beaſts of the Forreſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, others impute it to the charge of thoſe, who firſt pleaded for <hi>Liberty of conſcience,</hi> and prevailed with <hi>Authority</hi> for connivence at themſelves; which they intending perhaps, only to be indulged to truly <hi>tender conſciences,</hi> (which ought to be regarded) that doore of <hi>Liberty</hi> being but a little opened, the <hi>violence</hi> of others widened, and kept open the door, for the reſt to ruſh in, and it could never ſince be ſhut.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Others lay it at the door of that <hi>Power,</hi> which repealed the <hi>Paenall Statutes,</hi> for not being preſent at <hi>Church,</hi> the place of <hi>publique</hi> meetings; which (ſay they) was an <hi>Implicit toleration</hi> for all Religions. This <hi>Key</hi> hath ſerved ever ſince to open the doores of all the <hi>conventicles</hi> in the Land; where every ſubtle <hi>Jeſuited Sect-maſter,</hi> hath free <hi>Liberty</hi> to vent his own poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Opinions, and none to controll him. Nothing (it is thought) hath more gratified the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> ſince theſe late troubles began, then that <hi>repeal.</hi> I wiſh, they (now at their leaſure) may conſider the <hi>miſchiefs</hi> done; who had their hands and <hi>votes,</hi> in that <hi>repeal.</hi> Theſe and ſome others, of the like nature, are the <hi>conject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:40475:4"/> that are made, concerning the <hi>riſe</hi> and original, of this grand <hi>Defection</hi> from the truth. I cannot but think, theſe, or ſome of theſe have done much towards our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>miſeries</hi> and <hi>Church-diſtractions:</hi> but I beleeve, there may be found, other <hi>cauſes,</hi> nearer and more <hi>ime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate,</hi> in the men themſelves, who have of late, made this <hi>Apoſtacie,</hi> this <hi>Shipwrack of the Faith:</hi> And they are theſe three, or one of them.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Ignorance, in many of our miſled <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> hath ſlaine ten thouſands. Ignorance, I ſay, of the very firſt and Fundamentall <hi>principles</hi> of Religion: people were never well <hi>catechiſed,</hi> or grounded in the truth; and ſo carried away with every <hi>new winde</hi> of Doctrine. The common <hi>prey</hi> of Seducers, of old were ſilly <hi>women,</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> not ſo much for age, as diſcretion: Look upon the followers of our <hi>new Maſters,</hi> and they are for the moſt part <hi>younglings</hi> of eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Sects, but moſt <hi>females,</hi> who from the begining were moſt capable of <hi>Seduction.</hi> There are many of theſe ſpeake with them, about the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of their own <hi>Sect</hi> or way, and they are ready and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to diſpute it; as about <hi>Infant-baptiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Church way</hi> &amp;c. But examine them about the <hi>points</hi> of <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> what Faith is, what Repentance &amp;c. They cannot give any reaſonable account. I my ſelf have known ſome, that were Zealous <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and the like, who could ſufficiently finde Language to cry down a <hi>Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> and Tythes, and raile at the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> who were ſo farre from ſpeaking the Language of Scripture in <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aineſt principles</hi> that they could not ſpeake <hi>reaſon</hi> or ſenſe, in their common diſcourſe. Little do moſt men thinke or know, what <hi>deſperate ignorance</hi> there is to be found, in moſt <hi>ordinary</hi> people; <hi>No marvell if Seducers, by good words and fair ſpeeches, deceive the hearts of the
<pb facs="tcp:40475:4"/> ſimple.</hi> Rom. <hi>16.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. Pride</hi> (if they have gotten any more then ordinary knowledge) pride of <hi>parts,</hi> pride of <hi>gifts, confidence</hi> of Spirit, <hi>nimbleneſſe</hi> of fancy, <hi>volubility</hi> of Tongue, &amp;c. theſe puffe up ſelf conceited Novices, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <hi>ſcorn</hi> and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, that they thinke themſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>abler</hi> then their <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> and wiſer then <hi>7</hi> men, yea <hi>7 Miniſters</hi> that are able to render a <hi>Reaſon</hi> for what they ſay or do; Theſe young <hi>Lapwings</hi> runne away, with the <hi>ſhell</hi> on their head; and forget by whom they had their <hi>hatching.</hi> Theſe turn <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Preachers,</hi> and ſcorn and diſdain thoſe from whom they borrowed their light. Nothing ſo much diſcovers a light and a vaine head, and the <hi>Levitie</hi> and falſity of their waies, as firſt that pride and ſcorn manifeſted to all not of their own way; and that <hi>railing</hi> and <hi>reviling</hi> of men, far better then themſelves for wiſdome and pietie. Truth makes men humble, eſpecially to thoſe ſuppoſed to be in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and that meerly out of conſcience: <hi>ſhewing all meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to all men for we ourſelves were ſometime fooliſh deceived &amp;c.</hi> Tit. <hi>3.3.</hi> But marke <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peters</hi> deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> who ſhould bring in damnable Hereſies: <hi>2 Pet. 2.10.12. Preſumptuous are they ſelf-willed, they are not afraid, to ſpeak evil of dignities: theſe ſpeak evil of the things they underſtand not &amp;c.</hi> That's a ſecond; <hi>Pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. Hyprocriſie;</hi> open, or ſecret <hi>corruption</hi> of mens hearts, doth often betray their <hi>heads</hi> into errours. This is the ſubject of the following <hi>Sermon;</hi> I muſt not here <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate</hi> my own diſcourſe. Only let me tell you my owne and others obſervation; It is too well known, that many (I will not ſay, most) of them, who have left the <hi>old truths,</hi> for new, and the <hi>old waies</hi> for others, are ſenſibly grown far more looſe and remiſſe, in the <hi>practicall</hi> parts of Religion,
<pb facs="tcp:40475:5"/> then they were, before they departed from us: even ſome of thoſe who pretend to the <hi>pureſt way</hi> of Religion, and <hi>ſtricteſt</hi> way of Church Government are become more <hi>care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi> of themſelves and Fam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, in ſecret and private du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; Men and women that once durst not omit, <hi>reading, praying, catechizing</hi> their families, now can neglect all: Holding it, ſome of them, a <hi>profanation</hi> for to teach their Chidren, any <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> or forme of Prayer, or to ſpeake of Scripture: But generally (which is obſervable) all the Sests cry down the <hi>morality</hi> of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> make every day, (that is, no day) a <hi>Sabbath:</hi> can make it a day of <hi>recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> or eaſe; and neglect the Aſsemblies: moſt of them (except the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who cry down <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>faſhions,</hi> upon another <hi>Monkiſh deſigne</hi>) are as <hi>faſhionable,</hi> in their <hi>haire</hi> and <hi>habits,</hi> as any the moſt <hi>vaine</hi> and gariſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; and call it a part of their <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Liberty: what may be the cauſe of theſe <hi>Defections,</hi> in opinion and practiſe? I feare ſome <hi>ſecret luſt,</hi> or corruption of their hearts, which accounted the former ſtrictneſs and <hi>preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of the way of Religion, their <hi>burden;</hi> and now is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by ſome Doctrines of Liberty. Hence it is, that they generally fly and <hi>forſake</hi> their old Teachers, who know their <hi>lives,</hi> and touch their <hi>luſts,</hi> and ſeek out ſuch as preach <hi>novell</hi> and <hi>high ſpeculations, with ſwelling words of vanity,</hi> which never <hi>ſtoop</hi> ſo low, as to touch their <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>wantoneſſe, Covetouſneſſe</hi> and worldly minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp;c. But theſe things are more fully proſecuted in the following Sermon; and I feare, I have held you too long from it, I commend it to your <hi>Honourable</hi> peruſall, and to the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> of God, upon all that ſhall vouchſafe to reade it: In him I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable;</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble Servant, for your furtherance in the truth.</hi> Daniel Cawdry.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my ſtudy;</hi> 
                  <date>July <hi>23. 1655.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40475:5"/>
            <head>A late Great SHIPWRACK OF FAITH: Occaſioned by the VVrack of Conſcience.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 TIM. 1.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Which (good Conſcience) ſome having put away concerning the Faith have made ſhipwrack.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the <hi>life</hi> of a Chriſtian man in generall,<note place="margin">1. The cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> (in regard of the miſeries of it,) So the life of a <hi>Man of God,</hi> a Miniſter in ſpeciall, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a <hi>wayfare,</hi> to a <hi>warrefare,</hi> to a <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</hi> To a <hi>wayfare,</hi> and ſo the Miniſter is called a <hi>Guide,</hi> Rom. 2.19. <hi>a Guide of the blinde:</hi> To a <hi>warrefare,</hi> and here he is called a <hi>Captaine,</hi> or <hi>Leader,</hi> Heb. 13.17. <hi>obey</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>your Leaders;</hi> To a <hi>Seafare,</hi> (in the metaphor of the text) and then he may be called the <hi>Pilot</hi> of the ſhip, the <hi>Church:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.5.</note> The Apoſtle makes uſe of two of theſe <hi>Metaphors</hi> in the former, and this preſent verſe, there he bids him, <hi>Warre a good warrefare,</hi> as a chief
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40475:6"/> Commander, <hi>(according to the propheſies which went before upon him.)</hi> Here he bids him, as a <hi>Pilot,</hi> take heed of a <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack,</hi> by the example of others, that have miſcarryed, and preſcribes the <hi>meanes</hi> for both, <hi>Holding faith and a good conſcience, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. The expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the words to Faith, taken</note>For the <hi>explication</hi> of the words, we ſhall enquire,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is meant here by Faith: Faith is taken either <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectively,</hi> for the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Faith, <hi>quam credimus,</hi> which we do beleeve: or <hi>Subjectively,</hi> for the <hi>habit</hi> of Faith: and that 1.<note place="margin">1. Objectively. 2. Subjectively for the habit. 1. Actively. 2. Paſſively for Fidelity.</note> 
               <hi>Actively, Quâ credimus Deo,</hi> whereby we beleeve in God. 2. <hi>Paſſively, Ob quam creditur nobis,</hi> for which others believe and truſt us, that is, <hi>Fidelity,</hi> or <hi>faithfulneſs;</hi> and ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is taken, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. The fruits of the Spirit, are <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Faith;</hi> where it is taken, not for <hi>juſtifying faith,</hi> but for <hi>fidelity</hi> and faithfulneſs to others. It is taken here in the firſt ſenſe, <hi>objectively</hi> for the <hi>Doctrine of Faith,</hi> or <hi>Truth</hi> of the Goſpel, as the parrallel place manifeſts, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.18.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.21. Tit. 1.9. Faithful word.</note> ſpeaking of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> (one of the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> there) and <hi>Philetus,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>They have erred concerning the Truth,</hi> as here they are ſaid, <hi>To have made ſhipwrack concerning the Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience two wayes. 1. Of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility. 2. Of Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note>2. What is meant by <hi>good conſcience: Conſcience</hi> is nothing but a <hi>reflect Act</hi> of the ſoul upon it ſelf, applying <hi>Science</hi> or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to a mans ſelf, and ſo approving or diſproving, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or excuſing. The <hi>goodneſs</hi> of the conſcience is either the goodneſs of <hi>Tranquility,</hi> a peaceable conſcience, or the goodneſs of <hi>integrity,</hi> or ſincerity, a practical conſcience, walking according to its knowledge So <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Act.</hi> 23.1. <hi>I have in all good conſcience walked before God,</hi> which 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. is called,<note place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note> 
               <hi>a pure conſcience.</hi> And by our Saviour, in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the <hi>ſeed,</hi> its called a <hi>good and an honeſt heart,</hi> which is expreſſed, by a <hi>Religious and honeſt converſation.</hi> In this ſenſe, it is here taken.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Holding, or Having.</note>3. What is meant by <hi>Holding;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>having</hi> is the word; but being of the Preſent Tenſe, it implies a <hi>continued Act,</hi> and ſo is well rendered, by <hi>Holding;</hi> firſt get it and have it, then hold it; yea more ſignificantly, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40475:6"/> faſt the faithful word, according to doctrine,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The next word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>having put away;</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Put away.</note> which ſignifies an act, not of ignorance or infirmity, but knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and willingly, to <hi>refuſe</hi> or <hi>reject</hi> the dictates of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; <hi>repellentes,</hi> repelling, or rejecting the verdict of it: The ſame word is uſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.27.<note place="margin">Act. 13.46. Put it from you <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Of the man that quarrelled with <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he thruſt him away.</hi> It imports a kind of <hi>violence</hi> offered to conſcience, by walking contrary to it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The laſt word conſiderable is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">5. Made ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack.</note> 
               <hi>have made ſhipwrack;</hi> a <hi>Metaphor</hi> taken (as I ſaid) from <hi>Mariners</hi> or Seafaring men, who when the <hi>Ship</hi> is broken or ſunk, loſe the <hi>Merchandize</hi> therein contained. So that <hi>Faith,</hi> or the <hi>Truth</hi> of the Goſpel is the <hi>Merchandize;</hi> a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> is the Ship. <hi>Faith</hi> is the <hi>Jewel,</hi> a good conſcience is the <hi>Cabinet;</hi> Faith is the <hi>Treaſure,</hi> a good conſcience is the Cheſt or <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury.</hi> If the <hi>Ship, Cabinet, Cheſt</hi> miſcarry, the <hi>Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, Iewel, Treaſure</hi> cannot be ſafe.</p>
            <p>The full ſenſe and <hi>ſum,</hi> is this,<note place="margin">3. The ſum of words.</note> 
               <hi>If thou (O</hi> Timothy) <hi>wilt war a good warfare, or fulfill thy</hi> Seafare <hi>with comfort and commendation, Hold faſt Faith, that is, the Truth of the Goſpel, but eſpecially hold faſt a good conſcience which is the Ship or Cabinet; for that being loſt, or put away, the Faith will be loſt inevitably, as the ſad and lamentable example of ſome,</hi> Himeneus <hi>and</hi> Alexander <hi>doth manifeſt; who having put a good conſcience away concerning the Faith, have made Shipwrack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words being thus explained, hold out unto us,<note place="margin">The Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made good <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Chrſ. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </note> this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, which I ſhall deliver in <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> words upon the place. <hi>A corrupt and a culpable life breeds a corrupt judgement; an unſound heart makes an unſound</hi> head: if a man put away a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> he will ſoon make <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack</hi> of the <hi>Faith.</hi> As the <hi>conſcience</hi> cannot be <hi>good,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Faith be <hi>pure;</hi> ſo the <hi>Faith</hi> cannot be <hi>ſafe,</hi> unleſs the conſcience be <hi>good.</hi> Without knowledge the minde is not good, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.2. A corrupt <hi>judgement,</hi> makes a corrupt <hi>life</hi> or conſcience; and a corrupt <hi>conſcience,</hi> will ſoon corrupt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40475:7"/> the <hi>Faith</hi> which was thus we ſhall make good.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. From Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</note>1. By parallel places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> we have the like (in a leſſer degree) in this very <hi>Chapter,</hi> verſ. 5, 6, 7. <hi>The end of the commandment is</hi> Love, <hi>out of a pure heart, good conſcience, and faith unfained;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>which (pure heart, good conſcience,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>ſome having ſwerved from, have turned to vain janglings.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor</hi> taken from <hi>Archers,</hi> who miſtake their <hi>aime,</hi> and ſo miſs the <hi>mark.</hi> The meaning is, ſome deſiring to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Doctors or teachers of the Law,</hi> not levelling or <hi>aiming</hi> at <hi>purity</hi> of heart, and a good <hi>conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. they have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to decline from the <hi>Truth,</hi> being turned to vain <hi>janglings.</hi> What is that? <hi>Fables, and endleſs or uſeleſs genealogies, which breeds queſtions rather then Godly edifying, which is by faith, verſ.</hi> 4. Theſe vain <hi>diſputations,</hi> as they take men off from <hi>practical Truths,</hi> ſo they do by little and little <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt</hi> the truth. To the like purpoſe, the Apoſtle preſcribes this as a <hi>preſervative</hi> of the Faith, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.9. to his <hi>Deacons, Holding the myſtery of the Faith in a pure Conſcience. Pure faith,</hi> will not abide but in a <hi>pure conſcience,</hi> as the <hi>Doves</hi> a cleanly creature,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> will not abide but in a <hi>clean</hi> houſe. And on the contrary, ſee 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. theſe two go together, <hi>Men of corrupt minds (that is conſcience) deſtitute or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the truth. He had ſaid before,</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe, and conſenteth not to the wholſome words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to godlineſs.</hi> In the 4 and 5 verſes, he gives the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that corrupting the Faith: partly his <hi>pride,</hi> he is <hi>puffed</hi> up; partly his ignorance (acquired perhaps) <hi>he knoweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but dotes</hi> about queſtions, and partly, yea chiefly, <hi>He is a man of a corrupt mind;</hi> and therefore juſtly <hi>deprived</hi> of the knowledge of the truth. The very like expreſſion is in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. ſpeaking of <hi>ſeducers</hi> of themſelves and others, <hi>that lead captive ſimple women;</hi> he ſhewes the reaſon of both: They <hi>ſeduce</hi> others, whom? ſuch as have <hi>loſt,</hi> or never had a good conſcience, <hi>Simple women laden with ſins, and led about with divers luſts.</hi> They are themſelves <hi>ſeduced</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40475:7"/> upon the ſame ground, <hi>men of corrupt mindes;</hi> then follows, <hi>reprobate concerning the faith,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men that have loſt their <hi>judgement</hi> concerning the <hi>Truth</hi> of the Goſpel. And <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. he ſayes, <hi>Evil men and</hi> ſeducers <hi>wax worſe and worſe (not onely in life, but alſo in judgement, for ſo it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) deceiving and being deceived.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.5. Suppoſing that gain is godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, through covetouſneſs</note> Firſt their <hi>life</hi> corrupts their judgement, and their <hi>judgement</hi> again corrupts their life. Its ſtrange to conſider how far a mans <hi>judgement</hi> may be corrupted by a bad <hi>conſcience</hi> and wicked converſation: Take but one place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. <hi>The fool hath ſaid in his heart there is no God.</hi> How comes it to paſs that a man ſhould be ſo groſly <hi>corrupted</hi> in ſo clear a <hi>principle?</hi> The <hi>works</hi> of God proclaim a God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19. <hi>That which may be known of God,</hi> &amp;c. How come men to think there is no God? the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon follows: <hi>Corrupt are they and become abhominable in their doings, &amp;c.</hi> This is rendred as a reaſon, why the Prophets and Prieſts corrupted the Law of God, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Her Prophets are light and treacherous perſons; her Prieſts have polluted the Sanctuary, they have done violence to The Law.</hi> More might be added, but theſe may ſuffice for inſtances. We ſhall now manifeſt it further.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Reaſons: How comes it to paſs,<note place="margin">2. By Reaſons.</note> that the <hi>corruption</hi> of the <hi>heart</hi> or <hi>life,</hi> hath ſuch influence to corrupt the head or judgement in the plain <hi>Truthes</hi> of the Goſpel? Take theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Sinful luſts</hi> (allowed and lived in) <hi>hinder ſpiritual light</hi> and ſaving knowledge. <hi>Luſts</hi> are like <hi>ſcales</hi> upon the eyes,<note place="margin">1. Sinful luſts hinder ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al light.</note> like a webb or <hi>cataract</hi> (as they call it) that covers the ſight of the eye of the ſoul: And therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> makes <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> (which is the <hi>removal</hi> of thoſe luſts) the way to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledge, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. <hi>If at any time God will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the Truth.</hi> It was well ſaid of a <hi>Divine</hi> of ours, that <hi>Repentance is the</hi> Miniſters <hi>beſt Comment upon his text, and the</hi> hearers <hi>beſt Comment upon the Sermon.</hi> So 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. ſpeaking of the <hi>Jews, When their heart ſhall be turned to the Lord (by true repentance) the vail of ignorance and blindneſs) ſhall be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40475:8"/> taken away.</hi> Hence are thoſe promiſes of knowledge made to the Godly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord,</hi> is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>The meek will he guide in judgement, and the meek will he teach his way.</hi> And verſe 12. <hi>What man is he that feareth the Lord? him ſhall he teach in the way that he ſhall chooſe.</hi> So <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 2.26. <hi>To him that is good in his ſight, God giveth wiſdom and knowledge.</hi> And our Saviour himſelf,<note place="margin">See Joh. 8.31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17. <hi>If any man will do his will, he ſhall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God, or whither I ſpeak of my ſelf.</hi> If a man reſolve to <hi>hold the truth unrighteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.18. 2 Tim. 2.6, 7.</note> not letting it break out in his practice, God will not do that man the honor to let him know the truth: we our ſelves would not impart our skill to ſuch <hi>Schollars,</hi> as we know, would not make uſe of it. It was (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> well obſerves) a ſtrange thing, that <hi>David</hi> ſo wiſe a man,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Chryſ. Tom.</hi> 1. pag. 697.</note> and a <hi>Prophet,</hi> ſhould go about to hide his ſin, not onely from men, but prehaps from God too: He gives the reaſon of it, <hi>Though he was a Prophet, yet luſt had blinded his eyes, and darkned his underſtanding:</hi> That's the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. They put out Natural and Artificial light.</note>2. <hi>Sinful luſts,</hi> put out <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>artificial</hi> light. All ſin is of an infatuating and <hi>darkening</hi> nature, it either finds or makes men <hi>fools.</hi> It is not for nothing that <hi>ſinners</hi> are ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten called <hi>fools,</hi> and ſin <hi>folly,</hi> by <hi>Solomon,</hi> and others; or that ſins are called by the name of <hi>ignorances, Heb.</hi> 9.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the errors or <hi>ignorances of the people.</hi> They are mutual <hi>cauſes</hi> one of another; many (if not moſt) <hi>ſins</hi> are cauſed from ignorance, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do, and much</hi> ignorance <hi>is procured from ſin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nemo malus niſi ſtultus, enim ſaperet bonus eſſe mallet, <hi>Salv.</hi>
               </note> If men were not <hi>fooliſh,</hi> they would never venture to ſin: and if ſome did not ſin ſo much, they ſhould be <hi>wiſer</hi> then they are: <hi>no man (ſayes</hi> Salvian) <hi>is evil but a fool, for if he were wiſe, he would be good.</hi> Sins are called <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and works of darkneſs, becauſe as they proceed from, ſo they end in <hi>darkneſs,</hi> inward darkneſs of the mind, and outter darkneſs of death and hell, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40475:8"/> As the crude and <hi>cold darkneſs</hi> of the night thickens the clouds and thoſe clouds, thickned, increaſe the darkneſs of the night: So the <hi>ignorance</hi> of men, caſts them into <hi>lusts,</hi> and thoſe luſts blind their reaſon and <hi>judgement:</hi> See it in the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21, 22. <hi>Becauſe when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankful; they became vain in their imaginations, and their fooliſh heart was darkened, profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be wiſe, they became fools,</hi> Groſſe fools a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the very light of nature, as appears in the next verſe. <hi>They changed the glory of God the incorruptible into an image made like corruptible man, and to birds and four footed beaſts and creeping things.</hi> So the Apoſtle of ſome others, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Having their underſtanding darken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> How? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>by the hardneſs of their hearts:</hi> An hard and <hi>callous</hi> humor grow over their eyes by <hi>cuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> ſinning, as it follows; <hi>Being paſt feeling, they gave themſelves over unto laſciviouſneſs, to work all uncleanneſs with greedineſs.</hi> Our own <hi>experience</hi> may afford us <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi> of this kind, too many; Men of <hi>excellent</hi> parts of <hi>Nature, Art, Learning,</hi> beſotted and <hi>befooled</hi> in their <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and given over to as <hi>vile errors</hi> as luſts; well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>deceitful luſts,</hi> Eph. 4.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. or <hi>luſts of deceit,</hi> becauſe they <hi>ſeduce</hi> and deceive their owners.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sinful lusts,</hi> if they do not put out the <hi>light</hi> of reaſon,<note place="margin">3. They cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Reaſon and turn it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth.</note> yet they <hi>corrupt</hi> and bribe it, and <hi>imploy the ſtrength of it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves and oppoſe the truth.</hi> See that place 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to wholeſome words, &amp;c.</hi> He is puffed up and <hi>dotes (ſo we read it)</hi> the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>he is ſick;</hi> and as ſick ſtomacks deſire <hi>unwholſome</hi> food, ſo a <hi>ſin-ſick ſoul,</hi> cannot endure <hi>ſound doctrine</hi> (as he ſpeaks of others, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.) but ſtudious how to plead for his own luſts and errors: So the Apoſtle adds, <hi>Whence cometh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, ſtrife,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>perverſe diſputings and wranglings of men of corrupt minds:</hi> So corrupt that they <hi>eſteem gain to be godlineſs.</hi> How comes this to paſs? Why, they <hi>diſpute,</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> themſelves into theſe groſes <hi>opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40475:9"/> So that luſts, not onely <hi>corrupt</hi> reaſon, but turn the <hi>edge</hi> of it againſt the truth, to maintain <hi>gainful</hi> errors and practices; ſtudy new <hi>diſtinctions</hi> and new <hi>niceties,</hi> to quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the groſſeſt <hi>obſurdities.</hi> We could hardly <hi>believe</hi> this; did we not ſee it in experience. The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> firſt plotted a <hi>Religion</hi> full of ſuperſtitious <hi>formalities,</hi> to uphold their own <hi>luſts, pride, ambition, covetouſneſs, voluptuouſneſs;</hi> and then ſet their beſt <hi>wits</hi> on work to maintain it, with <hi>nice diſtinctions,</hi> and <hi>Scholaſtical</hi> ſpeculations, deceiving their <hi>followers</hi> ſo long, that at laſt they <hi>deceived</hi> themſelves, and believed their own <hi>deluſions</hi> to be truths. So it hath been, I fear, with ſome of the <hi>Arminian</hi> and <hi>Socinian</hi> party; who the better to maintain their own luſts, have patronized with much ſubtilty thoſe <hi>Pleagian</hi> doctrines, of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Freewill,</hi> &amp;c. And divers practices, formerly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by all <hi>Divines,</hi> or the moſt, as <hi>uſury,</hi> &amp;c. are now ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and upheld by <hi>ſoft diſtinctions</hi> and tender qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. They cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</note>4. <hi>Sinful luſts</hi> allowed, <hi>&amp;c. corrupt the affections, and they corrupted, corrupt the judgement.</hi> All judgement (we uſe to ſay) is loſt, when the <hi>Affections</hi> are truſted with the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the caſe. From hence (the <hi>affections</hi> corrupted) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds: Firſt, a <hi>ſtrangeneſs</hi> to the light, <hi>He that evil does (and loves to do it) comes not to the light, leaſt his deeds ſhould be reproved,</hi> Joh. 3.20. or diſcovered to be evil: <hi>He that doth truth, cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that they are wrought in God.</hi> Can a thief or deceiver <hi>love</hi> or like the light, that betrayes him? 2. Yea more then this, he loves darkneſs, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. becauſe his deeds are evil. 3. But more then this, he not onely grows <hi>ſtrange</hi> to the light and loves darkneſs, but <hi>hates the light,</hi> as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour there ſpeaks. When <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> would needs enquire if there were never a <hi>Prophet</hi> of the Lord to conſult with; <hi>Yes</hi> (ſayes <hi>Ahab) there</hi> is a fellow, <hi>one Michaiah, but I hate him, for he never propheſies good to me, but evil: Ahab</hi> was reſolved upon his own <hi>project</hi> to go againſt <hi>Ramoth Gilead:</hi> and he fears honeſt <hi>Michiaah</hi> will croſs him in it; therefore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40475:9"/> he not onely <hi>avoids,</hi> but hates him: So deal <hi>reſolved ſinners</hi> with the <hi>light</hi> of the word: firſt grow <hi>ſtrange</hi> to it, neglect to read or hear it, and after come to hate it. He that loves his <hi>luſts</hi> cannot love the <hi>word</hi> that reproves them; but leaſt the word ſhould <hi>correct</hi> him, he will <hi>correct,</hi> indeed corrupt the word. Hence comes it, that men <hi>Having itching ears af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their own luſts, they get themſelves an heap of teachers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> ſuitable to their luſts, ſo the words may be read, <hi>If a man will propheſie of wine and ſtrong drink; he ſhall be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet for the people,</hi> Mich. 2.11. That is, they being given to <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſs,</hi> love and <hi>like,</hi> and ſeek out <hi>Prophets, good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows</hi> like themſelves, that will indulge them in ſuch courſes: And they ſay to their <hi>teachers,</hi> as the meſſengers ſent for <hi>Michaiah</hi> ſaid to him,<note place="margin">2 King. 22.13.</note> 
               <hi>All the Prophets ſpeak good unto the King with one mouth; let thy word, I pray thee, be like the word of one of them, and ſpeak good.</hi> So theſe kind of men, enquire the <hi>judgement</hi> of their Miniſters concerning ſome doubtful practice, <hi>uſury, gaming, faſhions,</hi> &amp;c. and they tell them, ſuch and ſuch <hi>allow</hi> it, I pray, let your word be as one of them: And mark the iſſue; If but <hi>one</hi> or a <hi>few</hi> men agree with them, they ſhall be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt <hi>thouſands</hi> that condemne the practiſe. As <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſaid of the <hi>perſecutors</hi> of the Chriſtians, <hi>They believe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations which are not proved; nor do they deſire to try them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Credunt quae non probantur, nec quaerunt ne non probantur, <hi>Apol.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>leaſt they ſhould not be proved;</hi> So is it here, they eaſily <hi>believe</hi> what they would fain have to be true; and what they like not, they will hardly believe. This then is a <hi>fourth</hi> reaſon; <hi>Sinful luſts</hi> corrupt the <hi>Affections,</hi> and the <hi>Affections</hi> corrupt the judgement.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Sinful luſts,</hi> do <hi>ſtupifie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. They ſilence or ſtupifie the Conſcience by corrupting the truth.</note> 
               <hi>conſcience or ſilence the clamor of it, by corrupting the Truth.</hi> Hence you hear of ſome, <hi>That have made a Covenant with death, and with hell: are they at agreement?</hi> Iſa. 28.15. that is, have <hi>ſilenced</hi> their fears of <hi>death</hi> and <hi>hell,</hi> by ſome lying and falſe <hi>perſwaſions</hi> of peace, notwithſtanding their ſinful practiſes, as the Prophet inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates in the following words, <hi>For we have made lies our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and under falſhood have we covered our ſelves.</hi> There is in ſinful practiſes a <hi>ſting</hi> of terror and horror of <hi>guilt,</hi> till
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40475:10"/> this be either <hi>taken</hi> out by repentance and pardon, or at leaſt <hi>ſtupified</hi> and laid aſleep, the ſoul cannot quietly enjoy the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of ſinning. This cannot well be done, in a <hi>knowing Chriſtian</hi> but by corrupting the <hi>Faith.</hi> Reſolved they are, not to diſeaſe or diſquiet <hi>conſcience,</hi> by ſo much as queſtioning the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of their practiſe. As the <hi>Athenians</hi> having ſhamefully loſt <hi>Salamis,</hi> a Town of their juriſdiction, made a <hi>Law,</hi> that no man ſhould once name <hi>Salamis. Aquinas</hi> upon 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. applies it to uſurers and ſuch like, <hi>Many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful things</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>are forbidden by ſound doctrine, which men are unwilling to forſake, and ſo they find out a new doctrine, where they may have ſome hope to be ſaved in theſe courſes.</hi> We need not go far for an inſtance, <hi>Hymeneus</hi> (one of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates</hi> mentioned in the text) together with <hi>Philetus,</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the <hi>Faith</hi> in a prime Article of it, the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the dead, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17, 18. <hi>Their word will eat as a canker: of whom is</hi> Hymeneus <hi>and</hi> Philetus, <hi>who concerning the truth have erred,</hi> ſaying, <hi>that the Reſurrection is paſt already: and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the faith of ſome.</hi> What was the reaſon of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the <hi>Faith?</hi> I will give it you in the words of a judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Interpreter upon the place, <hi>Becauſe they could not bear an accuſing conſcience, and the torment thereof, they undertake to defend their vices: and leaſt they ſhould be vexed with the terror of future judgement; they deny any providence, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves, that theſe things are falſe, which the true Faith and Religion declare concerning the immortality of the ſoul, the Reſurrection of the body and the laſt judgement.</hi> If their <hi>practiſes</hi> will not agree with the <hi>word,</hi> they conſtrain the <hi>word</hi> to agree with their <hi>practiſe:</hi> That's a fifth Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin">6. The Juſt judgement of God.</note>6. Laſtly, <hi>It is the juſt judgement of God</hi> upon ſuch ſinners: when men, for the maintenance and allowance of their <hi>own luſts,</hi> will not <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>light</hi> of truth, they ſhall not ſee it, <hi>That he</hi> (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> well) <hi>who knowing what is right , would not do it, at length ſhould come to be ignorant what is right;</hi> we have inſtances enough, both in Jews, Gentiles, and Chriſtians. In Jews, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.8, &amp;c. <hi>Hear O my people, and I will teſtifie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40475:10"/> thee, if thou wilt hearken unto me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But my people would not hearken unto my voice, and Iſrael would none of me,</hi> verſ. 11. What followed? <hi>So I gave them up to their own hearts luſts, and they walked in their own counſels:</hi> Let them follow their own <hi>Imaginations,</hi> corrupting the <hi>truth</hi> of God, by their corrupt <hi>lives</hi> and practiſes. In Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. <hi>The wrath of God is revealed from heaven, againſt all ungodlineſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> How or wherein doth this wrath appear? See <hi>verſ.</hi> 21, 22. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that when they knew God, and glorified him not as God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they became vain in their imaginations, and their fooliſh heart was darkened.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. <hi>God gave them up to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, through the lusts of their own heart,</hi> &amp;c. even to moſt <hi>unnatural luſts,</hi> not fit to be named, <hi>verſ.</hi> 26, 27. <hi>And for this cauſe God gave them up to a reprobate minde, to do things which are not convenient,</hi> verſ. 28. In <hi>Chriſtians</hi> we have it threatned, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10, 11. abundantly made good upon the followers of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> of whom he ſayes, <hi>Whoſe coming is after the working of Satan, with all power and ſigns, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders: And with all deceiveableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, in them that periſh; becauſe they received not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved. And for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions that they ſhould believe a lie. That they all might be damned, who believed not the truth, but had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> And thus we have finiſhed the <hi>Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal part</hi> of our diſcourſe, <hi>That a corrupt heart makes a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt head: An unſound heart makes an unſound judgement.</hi> Let us now proceed to the <hi>Application.</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. Application Uſe 1. To ſhew the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation of our Nature.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Take notice of the miſerable and lamentable <hi>Deprava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of our nature, ſince our firſt <hi>Father</hi> affected too much knowledge, <hi>to be like God, knowing good and evil.</hi> We are now our own worſt enemies; and our <hi>corruptions</hi> begins at our ſelves. It is a queſtion (yet no great queſtion) Whither <hi>Adams</hi> underſtanding, or his affections were firſt corrupted? This is certain, that both wayes now we are ſubject to <hi>corruption.</hi> Sometimes the <hi>head</hi> corrupts the <hi>heart,</hi> A corrupt judgement corrupts the affections: <hi>Without</hi> (ſound) <hi>knowledge, the minde
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40475:11"/> is not good,</hi> Prov. 19.2. Sometimes the <hi>heart, affections,</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, corrupt the judgement: As it is in nature, there is a <hi>mutual influx</hi> or influence of the <hi>head</hi> upon the <hi>ſtomack,</hi> by <hi>diſtillations</hi> of ill humors; and of the <hi>ſtomack</hi> upon the <hi>head,</hi> by <hi>aſcenſion</hi> of ill ſomes or vapors; and both wayes the <hi>health</hi> of the body is endangered: So is it in the ſoul, a <hi>corrupt head,</hi> or an ill principled judgement, corrupts the heart and life; <hi>evil doctrines</hi> (as evil words) <hi>corrupt good manners,</hi> like <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grens,</hi> that eat and fret away the <hi>vitals</hi> of Religion, and the <hi>power</hi> of Godlineſs The Apoſtle was ſpeaking of ſome that were infected with this curſed principle, <hi>That there ſhould be no reſurrection.</hi> What <hi>influence</hi> would this doctrine have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart and life? See <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. <hi>Let us eat and drink for to morrow we dye,</hi> and there an end of us and all; <hi>Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>evil communications (evil doctrinal principles) corrupt good manners.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.33.</note> The <hi>judgement</hi> thus corrupted, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts the <hi>heart</hi> and life. And contrarily, a <hi>corrupt heart</hi> or life, corrupts the <hi>head:</hi> ſome evil practiſes <hi>ſophiſticate</hi> the judgement, and both wayes the <hi>health</hi> and ſalvation of the ſoul is hazarded.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Uſe 2. To manifeſt the Reaſon of the prevalence of of errors at all times.</note>2. We may ceaſe to wonder (for we ſee the reason) why <hi>ſeducers prevail ſo much</hi> upon people, and why the <hi>Church</hi> in all times, hath been peſtered with ſo much <hi>error,</hi> and falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. <hi>The hearts and lives of men corrupt their heads and judgements.</hi> Not to look too far back into the <hi>Primitive times,</hi> ſee it of latter dayes in the prevalence of <hi>Popery</hi> upon the world. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> foretold it ſhould come to paſs in the laſt dayes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>The ſpirit ſpeaketh evidently, that in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times, ſome ſhall depart from the faith, and ſhall give heed no errors and doctrines of divels, which ſpeak lies through hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</hi> What's the occaſion of it? <hi>Having their conſciences ſeared with an hote iron.</hi> Their conſciences were <hi>ſcorched</hi> and ſeared with <hi>groſe ſins,</hi> and then they corrupted the faith to <hi>heal</hi> them whole again. So 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Becauſe they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not the love of the truth; therefore God ſent them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhould believe a lye,</hi> verſ. 12. <hi>They believed not the truth.</hi> Why? <hi>becauſe they had pleaſure in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40475:11"/> We wondered, of late times, to ſee ſo many, not ſimple people onely, but learned <hi>Clerks</hi> and <hi>Rabbies,</hi> to turn <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſts, Arminians,</hi> Coſin-germanes of Papiſts: we needed not, if we had conſidered, that their <hi>hearts</hi> were gone to <hi>Rome</hi> before, and now their <hi>heads</hi> followed after. Were they well examined, many of them, it would be found, they firſt <hi>put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a good conſcience,</hi> before they <hi>made ſhipwrack of the Faith;</hi> their <hi>hearts</hi> betrayed their <hi>heads.</hi> Many of them were (its known they were) <hi>covetous, ambitious, voluptuous:</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> hath <hi>baits</hi> of all ſorts to catch them; that great <hi>Harlot</hi> and <hi>mother</hi> of <hi>fornications,</hi> hath a golden cup, full of <hi>prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, profits, pleaſures,</hi> and this made mens heads <hi>drunk</hi> and giddy, to embrace the groſſeſt errors &amp; obſurdities for truths. Look upon theſe preſent times and ſee what <hi>defection</hi> from the <hi>Faith</hi> there is, and what ſad <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from the old <hi>received Truths,</hi> is to be found amongſt us; and that not of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ignorant multitude (though they are a daily <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers) but of old <hi>profeſſors;</hi> who had not onely knowledge in the word (as they thought) but alſo a form of godlineſs in the worſt times. Our <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (I mean the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing party in it) ſeemed to me, not long ago, as a fair great <hi>looking glaſs,</hi> wherein was repreſented one onely <hi>Image:</hi> a ſweet <hi>unanimity</hi> and <hi>uniformity</hi> in judgement and affections. But now (Oh pitty!) its like the ſame <hi>glaſs</hi> broken into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>pieces,</hi> and every one preſenting a ſeveral <hi>Image,</hi> in ſo many ſects and factions almoſt as men: What may be the matter? Truely, I think <hi>mens hearts have betrayed their heads.</hi> They had a <hi>form,</hi> and but a <hi>form of Godlineſs,</hi> denying the <hi>power</hi> thereof, allowing themſelves in ſome open or ſecret <hi>corruption</hi>) and now juſtly delivered over to <hi>ſelf-pleaſing</hi> and ſelf-deceiving errors. Have you not ſeen in Summer time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a tree, an <hi>Apple,</hi> or a <hi>Pear,</hi> red and <hi>yellow-ripe</hi> afore all its fellows? Come next morning, and you find it on the ground. What was the matter? Why, there was a <hi>worm</hi> (as opening you find) at the <hi>Core,</hi> which ſucking up all the moyſture, haſtaned the outward ripening; and drew away that very <hi>ſap,</hi> that ſhould have preſerved it on the tree. So is it with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40475:12"/> many <hi>profeſſors,</hi> that in outward ſhews outrun many times, <hi>ſincere</hi> and honeſt hearted <hi>Coriſtians;</hi> making a more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhew of <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>practiſe,</hi> then other of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors (the <hi>ſtony ground</hi> brought forth fruit <hi>immediately,</hi> the <hi>good ground</hi> with patience) but there's a <hi>worme</hi> of ſome <hi>luſt</hi> within, that eats out the <hi>heart</hi> of Religion, <hi>hypocriſie</hi> haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on to ripeneſs of profeſſion, and then they fall off from the <hi>Faith</hi> to error. It were eaſie to inſtance, in almoſt all the preſent <hi>errors</hi> and <hi>heterodoxe</hi> opinions of the times; they are oftentimes entertained upon this very ground; becauſe they comply with and favor ſome open or <hi>ſecret luſt.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaking of ſome <hi>novel opinions</hi> of thoſe Primitive times (ſo early they began) calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, as well as vain bablings,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.16. and ſayes <hi>they grow to more ungodlineſs.</hi> Mark it, they ſuppoſe, and finde <hi>profane</hi> and ungodly hearts, and make them more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and ungodly hearts that intertain them: Do we not ſee the open looſeneſs of many formerly <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing hypocrites;</hi> as the <hi>event</hi> diſcovers? Do we not wonder at ſuch and ſuch <hi>zealous profeſſors,</hi> turned not onely <hi>erroneous</hi> in their judgements, but <hi>looſe</hi> and far more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious in their lives ſince they fell to theſe new opinions? Take but ſome few inſtances, of <hi>taking opinions,</hi> which in their very nature, are ſuitable to ſome mens corruptions; I told you heretofore of <hi>Hymeneus and Philetus,</hi> who fell into a groſs error, <hi>Saying that the Reſurrection was paſt already,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.17, 18. And the doctrine took exceedingly, <hi>Whoſe words fretted like a Gangrene, and overturned and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the faith of ſome.</hi> And have not we the ſame <hi>errors</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, now of late, in ſome that deny the <hi>immortality</hi> of the ſoul,<note place="margin">At the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our troubles the firſt Pamphlet that appeared, was of the Mortality of the ſoul.</note> and conſequently the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the body, and the <hi>laſt judgement?</hi> ſo did thoſe Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of; the <hi>falſe teachers</hi> he had ſpoken of, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. they made a <hi>mock</hi> of the laſt judgement, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. <hi>This firſt know, that in the laſt dayes ſhall come mockers, walking after their own luſts</hi> (mark that) <hi>ſaying, where is the promiſe of his coming?</hi> that is, to judgement. <hi>Willingly ignorant</hi> (ſayes he) of all thoſe grounds
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40475:12"/> that evidence the truth thereof; willing eaſily to <hi>believe</hi> there ſhould be none, becauſe they could heartily <hi>wiſh</hi> there might be none. And is not this <hi>pleaſing doctrine,</hi> to men that walk after their own <hi>luſts?</hi> Again, That curſed and <hi>blaſphemous</hi> doctrine, <hi>That God is the Author of mens ſins;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not of thoſe actions alone, in and with which ſin is, but of the very pravity, ataxy, anomy, irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs it ſelf, <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>Abfit. Abfit. Rom.</hi> 3.5 6. Pag. 37.</note> that its fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (though the <hi>Author</hi> be dead and the <hi>book</hi> burnt) lives in the heads and hearts of ſome, it not being then time to vent it, till a <hi>Tolleration</hi> of all Opinions be granted, and the times fitted to bear it: That <hi>opinion</hi> (I ſay) who are like to embrace it? Why, <hi>troubled ſouls</hi> (troubled with the horror of guilty conſciences, ſo for their comfort was it publiſhed) but trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, not <hi>Evangelically</hi> ſure, they need no ſuch comforts, but <hi>Legally</hi> that would fain <hi>enjoy</hi> their luſts, but dare not unleſs their conſciences be <hi>ſtupified</hi> with ſome ſuch doctrine as this, <hi>That God hath more hand in mens ſinfulneſs then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> Let me not multiply caſes, I will give you one inſtance of a <hi>luſts</hi> that troubles many, though in ſeveral wayes. Do you think the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſayes in vain, <hi>The ſpirit that is in us luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after liberty?</hi> Where doth the Scripture ſay ſo (you will ſay?) If it ſay ſo by conſequence, a fair deduction, I hope you will ſay, it ſays ſo. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hints ſo much, when he ſayes, <hi>Brethren, you are called unto liberty, only uſe not your liberty as an occaſion to the fleſh,</hi> Gal. 5.13. implying not onely a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, but a <hi>proclivitie</hi> in men, to abuſe their <hi>liberty.</hi> Now I am much deceived, if this be not the common <hi>bait</hi> of moſt <hi>ſeducers</hi> of theſe times; and that which ſubverts the <hi>Faith</hi> of many, but through their <hi>own luſts.</hi> It was fore-propheſied by Saint <hi>Peter</hi> of old, to come to paſs in theſe laſt times, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18, 19. He had ſaid in the beginning of the <hi>Chapter,</hi> verſ. 1. <hi>But there were falſe Prophets alſo among the people, even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers amongſt you, which privily bring in damnable hereſies,</hi> &amp;c. How ſhall they convey their poiſon? See <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>In ſpeaking ſwelling words of vainity, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile them that were a little eſcaped from them which are wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in error:</hi> What's the bait? <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. <hi>promiſing them liberty</hi> (&amp; are themſelves the ſervants of corruption) <hi>promiſing them liberty.</hi> But what betrayes them? <hi>much wantonneſs, through
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40475:13"/> the luſts of the fleſh:</hi> which luſteth after <hi>Liberty.</hi> I pray conſider, if this be not the <hi>Lure,</hi> that allures moſt of our <hi>Sectaries</hi> at this day. The <hi>Antinomians</hi> preach <hi>Liberty</hi> from the Law, <hi>Liberty</hi> from ſin, <hi>Liberty</hi> from Repentance, from ſorrow for ſin, <hi>Liberty</hi> from puniſhment, or chaſtiſement for ſin, <hi>Liberty</hi> from Duties, from the Sabbath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is not this a fine Doctrine for looſe <hi>libertine conſciences?</hi> The <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> preach <hi>Liberty</hi> from the power of the Magiſtrate (ſo ſome of them have, though others yet diſclaim it,) <hi>Liberty</hi> of propheſying or preaching, and adminiſtring Sacraments, to any ſuppoſed gifted brother; <hi>Liberty</hi> from Tythes, a <hi>taking doctrine,</hi> no queſtion, not like a <hi>Gangrene,</hi> but like <hi>wildfire.</hi> The <hi>Browniſt</hi> pleads for <hi>Liberty</hi> too, <hi>Liberty</hi> from Claſſes and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods Eccleſiaſtical, <hi>Liberty</hi> for the people to <hi>Govern</hi> and <hi>Vote</hi> in the Government of the Church, and to have <hi>power</hi> and Authority in the <hi>keyes,</hi> in <hi>election, ordination, excommunication,</hi> &amp;c. And how neer our Independent brethren of <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Old England</hi> come to them, in granting their people the <hi>key of Liberty,</hi> I would wiſh them to conſider; If all be true, which is reported, they find their peoples <hi>key of Liberty</hi> (in <hi>N. E.</hi>) hath almoſt devoured their <hi>Officers</hi> key of <hi>Authority,</hi> as <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod devoured all the reſt. But <hi>Liberty,</hi> deſire of <hi>Liberty</hi> in this and the like kind, is that, I fear, that <hi>wins</hi> them ſo many <hi>proſelytes.</hi> In a word, your <hi>Seekers</hi> (that have loſt their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and God knows when they will finde it) and thoſe that are for <hi>Toleration</hi> of all Religions, Quakers, and the like, do they not find ſpeedy <hi>acceptance</hi> and entertainment amongſt <hi>looſe-profeſſing Chriſtians?</hi> we may now ceaſe to wonder: we have ſeen the reaſon, <hi>A corrupt life corrupts the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this ſecond Uſe; Who are they ordinarily, that are the <hi>prey</hi> of <hi>ſeducers?</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath told you often: either very <hi>ſimple,</hi> or very <hi>ſinful;</hi> either <hi>weak</hi> in judgement, or <hi>ſtrong</hi> in luſts and paſſions. I ſhall inſtance but two places: The firſt is that in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Of this ſort are they that creep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to houſes</hi> (their qualities are afore deſcribed) <hi>and lead captive,</hi> Whom? Firſt, <hi>ſilly ſimple women,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>women,</hi> or <hi>men</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40475:13"/> as ſimple as <hi>women:</hi> people never very well principled in the grounds of Religion, <hi>alwayes learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth;</hi> and then follows their <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, laden with ſins and led about with divers luſts,</hi> pride and wantonneſs, ſcorn and bitterneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſecond place is in the 4 <hi>Chap.</hi> of the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>The time will come</hi> (and now its come) <hi>when they will not ſuffer wholſome or ſound doctrine, but having itching ears,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall get them an heap of teachers.</hi> What makes their ears <hi>itch</hi> thus, after variety of <hi>new teachers?</hi> their own <hi>ſeveral lusts: after their luſts, their own luſts, ſhall they get them an heap of teachers:</hi> that is, as I hinted afore; Teachers <hi>ſuitable</hi> to their ſeveral luſts. And thus, I have done with the ſecond Uſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may upon this <hi>ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Uſe 3. A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſtick of more Apoſtates</note> make a very probable <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſtick</hi> concerning the ſtate and condition of many men and women, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe who are <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>corrupt</hi> in their lives, not yet taken with any of the <hi>New old errors,</hi> and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>notions</hi> of theſe times: They are in a fair and ready way to <hi>Apostaſie;</hi> to be made a <hi>prey</hi> to one ſeducer or other, who can moſt <hi>ſutably</hi> ſcratch their <hi>itching ears,</hi> and comply with their <hi>own proper luſt. An</hi> unſound <hi>heart,</hi> will make an <hi>unſound head.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>perillous times,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> have fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned of to come to paſs in the laſt dayes,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1. 1 Tim. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>when many ſhall depart from the Faith.</hi> Theſe are <hi>diſcovering times</hi> if ever any were, as in the <hi>State,</hi> ſo in the <hi>Church. There muſt be hereſies, that theſe that are approved may be known.</hi> The men that ſhall be diſcovered, are largely deſcribed, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Lovers of themſelves, covetous, boaſters proud</hi> &amp;c. <hi>lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God.</hi> Yet <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Having a form</hi> (or figure) <hi>of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof.</hi> There are many already faln a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to <hi>believe</hi> lies and ſtrong deluſions upon thoſe corrupt practiſes; and aſſure your ſelves you that are ſuch, will not be long after them, if God put not a ſtop to the <hi>ſeducers</hi> of the times: Let no man ſay, <hi>Am I a dogge,</hi> that I ſhould fall to ſuch groſs opinions, ſuch <hi>horrid blaſphemies,</hi> ſuch Ranting practiſes. Aſſure thy ſelf, thy <hi>corrupt heart,</hi> will eaſily cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt thy <hi>head;</hi> If men be openly vitious, or <hi>ſecretly</hi> hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40475:14"/> and <hi>withhold the truth in unrighteouſneſs,</hi> it is not more <hi>ordinary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.11, 12.</note> then <hi>juſt</hi> with God, to give them up to <hi>believe a lie,</hi> that <hi>all they may be damned, that believed not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> And they that cannot endure <hi>ſound doctrine</hi> (the old wholeſome truths) becauſe it <hi>ſuites</hi> not with their <hi>luſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3, 4.</note> it is juſt with God, that as they <hi>turn their ears from the truth;</hi> ſo, they <hi>ſhall be given unto fables.</hi> That any <hi>ſecret</hi> or <hi>open hypocrites</hi> are not yet ſeduced, they may thank the <hi>providence</hi> of God, that hath preſerved them from the <hi>opportunities</hi> of Temptations,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.12.</note> and not their own <hi>ſtrength. An evil heart of unbelief, will cauſe men to depart from the living God.</hi> Look to it, <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that you be <hi>ſincere</hi> and keep a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> if not (theſe are <hi>winnowing</hi> and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering times) you will ere long (I dare be your <hi>Prophet,</hi> you will ere long) <hi>make ſhipwrack of the faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Avolent quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum volent paleae iſtae levis fidei, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Ile ſay no more of this but in <hi>Tertullians</hi> words, <hi>Let the chaff flye away as much as it will, the wheat will be the more in the floor of God,</hi> and we ſhall be the <hi>fitter</hi> for a <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Uſe 4. A cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to people, whom they truſt in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Mat. 7.16.</note>4. This may ſerve for <hi>Caution,</hi> a fair warning to people to take heed whom they <hi>truſt</hi> in matters of <hi>Faith</hi> and Religion. <hi>Beloved</hi> (ſayes Saint <hi>John</hi>) 1 Joh. 4.1. <hi>believe not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits whither they are of God, for many falſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are gone out into the world.</hi> How ſhall we try them? <hi>By their fruits you ſhall know them.</hi> Take heed of <hi>crediting</hi> too much thoſe men, thoſe <hi>Teachers</hi> whom you ſee looſe and <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt</hi> in their lives, and given over to <hi>Liberty,</hi> or rather <hi>licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs:</hi> Its twenty to one, they are, or will be <hi>unſound</hi> in their <hi>Judgements,</hi> who are <hi>unſound</hi> in their practiſe, at leaſt in that particular, wherein they <hi>allow</hi> themſelves. Will any man ask the advice, or reſt upon, the <hi>Judgement</hi> of a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous</hi> man concerning <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury?</hi> Or of a <hi>voluptuous</hi> man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Temperance</hi> and chaſtity? Or of a <hi>Libertine,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>ſtrictneſs</hi> of converſation? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, it is juſt with God, when <hi>Teachers</hi> are corrupted in their <hi>lives,</hi> in any one of thoſe, or the like <hi>luſts,</hi> to give them up to errors in <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to blind their own eyes, and ſo let them be <hi>blind lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the blind.</hi> Its true indeed, ſometimes <hi>falſe Prophets</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40475:14"/> come in <hi>ſheeps clothing;</hi> the greateſt <hi>ſeducers</hi> and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, have been men viſible of very <hi>ſtrict lives,</hi> that its hard for people to diſcover them without very <hi>ſerious</hi> obſervation. Yet a diligent watchful eye may do much: The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> had a very devout and <hi>Saint-like</hi> profeſſion: But yet our <hi>Saviour,</hi> both diſcerned, and diſcovered them; by a more <hi>ſpiritual ſin</hi> (if I may ſo call it) that is, by their <hi>pride.</hi> They <hi>prayed, faſted,</hi> gave <hi>alms,</hi> devoutly, frequently charitably, but all <hi>to be ſeen</hi> of men: <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>popularity,</hi> was their <hi>luſt</hi> and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. And this was very viſible in the <hi>Ancient Hereticks;</hi> very <hi>proud,</hi> and ſcornful. Thus (they ſay) <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Monke, that was ſent over into <hi>England,</hi> was diſcovered, by the advice of an holy <hi>Hermite,</hi> not to be a man of God. And this <hi>vice</hi> is viſible to half an eye, in many of our <hi>new Teachers,</hi> and many of their followers, they are a <hi>proud</hi> and <hi>ſcornful</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; undervaluing and <hi>trampling</hi> upon the reputation, of the moſt not onely <hi>learned,</hi> but <hi>pious</hi> and Godly <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the former and preſent times: I ſay no more, By <hi>their fruits</hi> you ſhall know them. Take heed whom you truſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The laſt Uſe ſhall be for <hi>Exhortation</hi> to all,<note place="margin">Uſe 5. Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to all.</note> both Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and people, To be <hi>careful,</hi> to hearken to the Apoſtles charge to <hi>Timothy; To hold Faith and a good Conſcience</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and as we deſire or intend, not to make <hi>ſhipwrack of the Faith;</hi> ſo to ſee, that we <hi>keep a good Conſcience.</hi> As you tender the preſervation of the <hi>Jewel,</hi> look well to the <hi>Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net; the better heart, the better head.</hi> For the more profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able preſſing home of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> give me leave to enlarge my ſelf a little. Firſt by a more particular <hi>d ſcovery</hi> of ſome <hi>ſpecial corrupti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> which experimentally Shipwrack the Faith. Secondly by <hi>urging</hi> ſome ſpecial <hi>motives,</hi> to people and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Thirdly, by preſcribing ſome directions to preſerve from <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſpecial <hi>corruptions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By diſcovering ſome ſpecial corruptions, as 1. Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> that moſt endanger the <hi>Faith</hi> to corrupt our <hi>Judgements,</hi> are theſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> nothing worſe to corrupt the <hi>Faith,</hi> then <hi>an heart exerciſed with covetouſneſs,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> ſpeaks, and notes it for one of the vices of <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40475:15"/> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 3. <hi>Through covetouſneſs ſhall they with fained words make merchandize of you,</hi> with 14, 15. <hi>Which forſaking the right way have gone aſtray, following the way of</hi> Balaam <hi>which loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs.</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly, <hi>The love of money, is the root of all evil, which while ſome have luſted after, they have erred concerning the Faith,</hi> 1 T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m. 6.10. So he deſcribes thoſe <hi>Cretian ſeducers,</hi> Tit. 1.10, 11. <hi>There are many diſobedient and vain talkers and deceivers, which ſubvert whole houſes, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucre ſake.</hi> And therefore he preſcribed this as one neceſſary <hi>qualification</hi> both of his <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Presbyter</hi> (for both are one, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. with 7.) and alſo of his <hi>Deacon,</hi> that they be <hi>not given to filthy lucre, not covetous,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.3. to this end, that he <hi>may hold faſt the faithful word,</hi> Tit. 1.9. Implying that if he be ſuch, he would ſoon <hi>corrupt</hi> the Faith. The holding of the Faith may coſt him the loſs of all his eſtate. Will a covetous heart ſuffer that? The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaw the experience of this in his time, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.13, 14. <hi>For from the leaſt of them, even unto the greateſt of them, every one is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to covetouſneſs, and from the Prophet to the Prieſt, every one dealeth falſly.</hi> Wherein? In the Faith, ſo it follows, <hi>They have healed the hurt of the daughter of my people ſlightly, ſaying, peace, peace, when there is no peace.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> clears himſelf from <hi>corrupting</hi> the word of God, by <hi>coloured covetouſneſs</hi> (as elſewhere he calls it) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17. <hi>We are not as many who corrupt the word of God</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Metaphor taken from <hi>Huckſters</hi> or <hi>Vintuers,</hi> who for lucres ſake, mingle water with their wine) <hi>but as of ſincerity, but as of God, in the ſight of God ſpeak we in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Ambition.</note>2. <hi>Ambition,</hi> or deſire of <hi>Domination,</hi> is another <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the Faith, eſpecially in <hi>corrupt times,</hi> when preferment cannot be had, but by <hi>complying</hi> with the errors of the times. We need not go far for inſtance, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the 7 verſ. of this Chap. gives a reaſon why ſome had turned to <hi>vain janglings,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Deſirous to be</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted) <hi>Teachers, or Doctors of the Law,</hi> as ſome now of the Goſpel) <hi>underſtanding neither what they ſay, nor whereof they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40475:15"/> affirme.</hi> Such a kind of <hi>ambitious</hi> perſon, was <hi>Diotrophes</hi> 3 <hi>Ep.</hi> of <hi>Joh.</hi> verſ. 9. who <hi>withſtood the Apoſtles doctrine</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the <hi>Churches.</hi> Why? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he loved the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence,</hi> he would be chief Biſhop himſelf. This was the occaſion of <hi>Arrius</hi> corrupting the Faith; his <hi>ambition</hi> to a Biſhoprick croſſed, and when his curſed <hi>Hereſie</hi> got head, and was countenanced by the <hi>Emperors,</hi> many turned <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> onely becauſe they ſaw <hi>preferment</hi> went that way. <hi>Cryſoſtom</hi> obſerved it long ago,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Chryſ. in 1 Tim. 5. hom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Hereſies grow out of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of ruling, becauſe they loved not their brethren</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>for want of love, they envyed thoſe that were in honor, from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy aroſe ambition or deſire of Ruling, from thence they ſell into Hereſies.</hi> To this purpoſe is that of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> 5.31. <hi>The Prophets propheſie falſly, and the Prieſts bear rule by their means,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Tremel. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> That is (ſayes the learned Tranſlator) the Prieſts did Lord it over Gods inheritance, by the aid of ſome falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> whom they allowed, and ſent abroad on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to procure them <hi>favour</hi> with the people. Why did they ſuffer the Truth to be ſo corrupted by the falſe Prophets? becauſe themſelves did bear Rule by their means. The <hi>Prieſts</hi> maintained them in their <hi>falſe doctrine,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Prophets</hi> maintained them in their <hi>falſe honor.</hi> Juſt as ſome Prelates did of late with us. To this head may be added, <hi>pride, popularity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pride.</note> and <hi>affection</hi> of <hi>ſingularity; pride</hi> is a great forerunner of falſe doctrine, <hi>pride goes before a fall,</hi> is true in this ſenſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi> The Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e therefore cautions, that his <hi>Biſhop</hi> or Elder, muſt not be a <hi>Novice,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a new convert to the <hi>Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Leaſt being lifted up (with pride) he fall into (Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie) the condemnation of the Divel,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.6. And one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>heterodox</hi> doctrine, is declared to be <hi>pride,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.45. <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He is proud, knowing nothing but doting about queſtions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>pride</hi> is his corruption; As <hi>pride</hi> of parts in many of our people, their (not very great) <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, utterance, expreſſion,</hi> gift of <hi>prayer,</hi> &amp;c. puffs them up that they <hi>ſwell</hi> above their ſphear, and caſts them into many dangerous errors: So in many of our young <hi>Miniſters,</hi> pride of their learning, gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The like doth that corruption of <hi>popularity,</hi> to be admired and applauded by the people,<note place="margin">Popularity.</note> by a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40475:16"/> multitude of <hi>followers,</hi> eſpecially if of the <hi>higheſt magnitude,</hi> rich, wiſe, noble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle noted this long ago, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.30. <hi>Alſo of your own ſelves ſhall ariſe men, ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things, to draw diſciples after them.</hi> So did thoſe falſe Apoſtles teach and preach for Circumciſion and the Law, to be joyned with Chriſt; upon what ground? <hi>They deſire to have you circumciſed</hi> (as ſome now rebaptize) <hi>that they may glory in your fleſh,</hi> that is, that they have drawn many to be proſelytes, to their way and opinion; and have a multitude of followers. Oh, for a poor ſimple fellow, a Miller, a Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be followed at heels with a troop of giddy diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; what a glory is this. Oh, to be pointed at, as <hi>the man.</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> is able to puffe up a young unballaſted ſpirit; and that's the way to be given over to, or held in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> did not ſo <hi>bewitch</hi> the people with <hi>ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> as the <hi>applauſes</hi> of the people did <hi>bewitch</hi> him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in his inchantments. He bewitched them, by giving it out, that himſelf was ſome great one, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.9. And they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched him with their applauſes, <hi>They all gave heed unto him from the leaſt to the greateſt, ſaying</hi> (mark that ſaying) <hi>This man is the great power of God. Singularity</hi> doth work the ſame effects, I mean deſire to be reputed <hi>ſingular;</hi> as many of our <hi>people</hi> (formerly of <hi>no great Religion</hi>) now <hi>Religion</hi> is come into <hi>faſhion,</hi> cannot content themſelves, to be wiſe to <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Singularity.</note> to be ſoberly Religious: but they aſpire after <hi>ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of <hi>opinions, new</hi> notions, <hi>new</hi> nothings indeed, and <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity</hi> of practiſe to be of the <hi>higheſt form</hi> of Religion, the <hi>Court Religion</hi> of the neweſt faſhion and dreſs So ſome of our <hi>preachers</hi> affect a <hi>ſingular</hi> way of preaching upon a common ſubject,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.18.</note> in an high, <hi>Meteorical, Metaphyſical</hi> ſtrain of notions and language, which (it may be) the Apoſtle calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>great, bunchy, ſwelling words of vanity,</hi> to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pefie and <hi>amuſe</hi> their unlearned Auditors. This is, as God ſpeaks to <hi>Job, to darken councel by words without knowledge, Job</hi> 38 2. The excellency of a true Miniſter, is to make ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure texts clear; theſe count it their excellency, to make clear texts obſcure. And who underſtand or admire them, except <hi>ignorant</hi> &amp; unlearned young men and <hi>ſilly women?</hi> but learned,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40475:16"/> 
               <hi>judicious,</hi> and ſubſtantial <hi>Chriſtians</hi> admire their vanity and folly. And what's the iſſue of all this <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>ſingularity?</hi> They many times <hi>ſtrain</hi> a truth ſo high,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.18.</note> that they <hi>break</hi> it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to errors, and miſlead <hi>ſimple,</hi> but ſometimes <hi>well meaning</hi> people. Take heed of theſe.<note place="margin">3. Voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Voluptuouſneſs,</hi> deſire of <hi>pleaſure</hi> and eaſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That this is an <hi>Inlet</hi> of errors and aberration from the <hi>Faith,</hi> is intimated by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1. <hi>Many ſhall depart from the faith,</hi> both Teachers and people. Why? not onely becauſe in general they have <hi>ſeared naughty conſciences;</hi> but for this in ſpecial, <hi>They are lovers of pleaſures, more then lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 3, 4.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.3.</note> Amongſt other qualfications of a <hi>Miniſters,</hi> the Apoſtle requires, that he be not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>given to wine,</hi> one that ſits at the wine (as the word imports) or <hi>tarries long at the wine,</hi> as the like phraſe is uſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.30. and of his <hi>Deacons,</hi> verſ. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not given to much wine,</hi> one that takes more heed to fill his <hi>luſts</hi> with wine, then his head with knowledge, or his <hi>heart</hi> with holineſs. Why this required? That he may <hi>hold the myſtery of the Faith in a pure conſcience,</hi> verſ. 9. Becauſe <hi>wine is a mocker,</hi> Prov. 20.1. that is, a <hi>deceiver,</hi> and takes away the heart, that is, his wiſdom: If you will ſee how far, look <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>Whoredome</hi> (another ſin of the voluptuous) <hi>and wine, and new wine takes away the heart;</hi> that is, the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, to run into the groſſeſt and moſt unreaſonable Idolatry: <hi>My people ask counſel at their ſtocks, and their ſtaffe declareth unto them, for the ſpirit of whordome hath cauſed them to erre, and they have gone a whoring from under their God.</hi> That's a famous place to this purpoſe, <hi>Iſa</hi> 28.7. <hi>But alſo they have erred through wine, and through ſtrong drink are out of the way; the Prieſt and the Prophet have erred through ſtrong drink, they are ſwallowed up of wine; they are out of the way through ſtrong drink they erre in viſion, they ſtumble in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> See alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 12. <hi>Her watchmen are blind, they are all ignorant, they are all dumbe dogs, they cannot bark, ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lying down, loving to ſlumber. Come ye</hi> (ſay they) <hi>I will fetch wine, and we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink, and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abundant.</hi> I will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40475:17"/> conclude this with one place more, an inſtance of an idle, <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſident</hi> Prophet or Miniſter, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.17. <hi>Wo to the idle ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd</hi> (that hath eyes and ſees not, <hi>&amp;c.) that leaves the flock:</hi> The unconſcionable <hi>Miniſter,</hi> that for his <hi>eaſe,</hi> pleaſure and idleneſs, neglects his <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and people. What ſhall be his puniſhment? <hi>The ſword ſhall he upon his arme, and upon his right eye; his arme ſhall be clean dryed up, and his right eye ſhall be utterly darkened.</hi> Experience of former times verifies this.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. Timerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note>4. <hi>Timer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſneſs,</hi> and fearfulneſs, in corrupt and perſecuting times, often betrayes the judgement unto <hi>compliance</hi> at leaſt, with the errors of the times. There were ſome <hi>falſe Apoſtles,</hi> that preached for <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the obſervation of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> together with the Goſpel: telling the people, that unleſs they were circumciſed, they could not be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. This was a very groſs perverting and <hi>corrupting</hi> of the Goſpel of Chriſt. What was it that thus miſlead and ſeduced them? partly to pleaſe and comply with others of that way and opinion, but chiefly their <hi>fearfulneſs</hi> to ſuffer for the truth of the Goſpel. So the Apoſtle reſolves it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>As many as deſire to make a fair ſhew in the fleſh, (that is, to pleaſe and not offend the Jews, ſtrictly cleaving to their</hi> old Law <hi>and Religion) they conſtrain you to be circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, onely leaſt they ſhould ſuffer perſecution for the Croſs of Chriſt.</hi> The ſame did in part betray <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> into <hi>diſſimulation</hi> of the truth, that they did not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, keep the right path of the truth of the Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.14. the reaſon is given, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>For before that certaine came from</hi> James, <hi>he</hi> (and <hi>Barnabas) did eat with the Gentiles, but when they were come, he withdrew and ſeparated himſelf, fearing</hi> (mark that fearing) <hi>them of the circumciſion.</hi> Fear of men wil betray mens <hi>judgements</hi> into error. How many in the Primitive times turned <hi>Arrians</hi> for fear of that perſecution under the <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhops and Emperors? How many, in the <hi>Marian</hi> times, turned to be <hi>Papiſts</hi> for fear of perſecution? And in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times. How many turned aſide to <hi>Arminian doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh ſuperſtitions,</hi> partly for <hi>favor</hi> and preferment, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for fear of the frowns and diſpleaſure of ſome in higher pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. To ſhut up this, As any <hi>luſt</hi> allowed and lived in, with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40475:17"/> the loſs of a good conſcience, will corrupt the Judgement. So eſpecially theſe four inſtanced in <hi>covetouſneſs, ambition, voluptuouſneſs, Timerouſneſs:</hi> Againſt all which, let me leave this to your ſerious conſideration: It is the opinion and Judgement of many learned, <hi>judicious,</hi> and Godly Divines,<note place="margin">Rev. 11.</note> that the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> are not yet, but are ſhortly to be <hi>ſlain;</hi> and that then, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> will once more (for a time prevail over the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> with the hotteſt perſecution that ever the <hi>Churches</hi> felt; which if it come to paſs (as God forbid, for we are not fitted for <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings</hi>) let all our looſe <hi>profeſſors</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at large (who allow themſelves to live in their open or ſecret luſts) and all thoſe, who are <hi>covetous, ambitious, voluptuous, time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> in ſpecial, <hi>know</hi> that they will (without more grace from God) as ſurely turn <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as now they profeſs <hi>Proteſtant:</hi> Their <hi>hearts</hi> will betray their <hi>heads:</hi> Their <hi>wrack</hi> of conſcience now, will then <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> the Faith. That's the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place, I ſhall preſs home,<note place="margin">2. The motive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the exhortation of the Apoſtle here, <hi>Hold faith and a good conſcience;</hi> in the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 4.23. <hi>Keep thy heart with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> or as the original hath it, <hi>Above all keeping, keep thy heart,</hi> thy conſcience; Deer Chriſtians, let it be your <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtudy,</hi> not to keep your <hi>eſtates, honors, liberties, lives,</hi> but your <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>conſciences:</hi> upon the reaſon implyed in the text, becauſe that's the onely way to <hi>keep the Faith.</hi> I ſhall not go far for <hi>motives,</hi> having ſtore, in and about the text; onely for <hi>methods</hi> ſake, I ſhall divide them into a double <hi>ſtream,</hi> betwixt <hi>you the people of God,</hi> and us <hi>Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To the people of God (and indeed to all) above all keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing keeping your <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>conſciences pure;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. To all the people of God, by 4 things.</note> I ſhall follow the <hi>Metaphor</hi> of the text; which ſpeaks of a <hi>Shipwrack:</hi> Here four particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the <hi>richneſs</hi> of the merchandize or <hi>Jewel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. The richneſs of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize the Faith.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with your <hi>Ship,</hi> your conſcience, is loaden and betruſted; It is, the Faith, that is (as you heard) the <hi>Truth;</hi> the <hi>Truth of the Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>Faith once</hi> (and but once) <hi>delivered to the Saints,</hi> Jude <hi>verſ.</hi> 3 which he exhorts all,<note place="margin">Prov. 23.23.</note> 
               <hi>earneſtly to contend for.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of meer men,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40475:18"/> cryes, <hi>Buy the truth, but ſell it not.</hi> Buy it at <hi>any price</hi> (as he the pearl, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.) but ſell it at no price; one <hi>ray</hi> of this Faith, this Truth, is more worth then all the world. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.13, 14 other <hi>merchandize</hi> cannot, but this will certainly make you for ever <hi>Happy:</hi> Hear what <hi>wiſdom</hi> it ſelf ſayes, <hi>Happy is the man that findeth wiſdom, and the man that getteth underſtanding; For the merchandize thereof, is better then the merchandize of ſilver, and the gain thereof, then fine gold. She is more precious then Rubies, and all the things thou canſt deſire, are not to be compared unto her. Length of dayes are in her right hand, in her left riches and honor; her wayes are wayes of plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntneſs, and all her paths are peace. She is a tree of life to them that lay hold upon her, and happy is every one, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth her.</hi> How careful are <hi>your merchants</hi> of the meaneſt commodities, if but <hi>Corn</hi> or <hi>Coals,</hi> &amp;c. to ſee them ſafe ſhipped in a good ſhip? much more, if loaden with precious <hi>merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize,</hi> Silk and Velvets, Silver, and Gold, and precious ſtones: would any wiſe man truſt theſe in a <hi>rotten, leaking</hi> Ship? The application is eaſily made, <hi>Faith</hi> is this <hi>Jewel,</hi> your <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> are the <hi>Ship;</hi> if you deſire to bring your <hi>Treaſure</hi> ſafe to land, have a care of the <hi>Ship</hi> your conſcience, that it be ſound and ſafe; If you <hi>put away a good conſcience,</hi> you muſt needs make <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> of the Faith, this <hi>incomparable</hi> Jewel. That's the firſt conſideration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Ship</hi> it ſelf, is next conſiderable. A good <hi>ſhip</hi> is long in making,<note place="margin">2. The good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſhip a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> great <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>coſts</hi> in rearing and rigging of it, and the uſe and comfort of it in a long and hard <hi>Seafare,</hi> is of great concernment, as a <hi>bad</hi> one fills with great fears. A <hi>good conſcience</hi> (which is here compared to the <hi>Ship</hi>) is a thing long in <hi>making,</hi> and coſt much to make it good, <hi>The blood of Chriſt to purge it from dead works, to ſerve the living God,</hi> Heb. 9.14. much <hi>pains</hi> and labor to keep it good, Act. 24.16. <hi>Herein I exerciſe my ſelf,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to have alwayes a conſcience void of offence toward God, and toward men.</hi> And for the uſe of it in this our <hi>Seafare,</hi> where we meet with <hi>ſtorms</hi> and <hi>pyrates,</hi> and ſhelves and rocks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nothing more ſafe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable then a <hi>good conſcience;</hi> good with the goodneſs of <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity,</hi> that will keep it good with the goodneſs of <hi>tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40475:18"/> A good conſcience is a continual feaſt,</hi> Prov. 15.15. And our Apoſtle who was (literally) in <hi>perils</hi> by Sea, as well as by land, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. and was often toſſed with the tempeſts of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, from the knowledge of the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of his ſhip, could ſing in a ſtorm (as if he had been in <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark) <hi>This is our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, the Teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſincerity not with fleſhly wiſdom, we have had our converſation in the world,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12. The Pſalmiſt ſings it out, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.165. <hi>Great is the peace which they have, who love thy law, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall offend them:</hi> or they ſhall have no <hi>ſtumbling blocks</hi> (as the <hi>original</hi> bears it) Nothing ſhall offend them, is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, more is meant then ſpoken; they are much <hi>pleaſed, delighted, raviſhed</hi> with the <hi>peace</hi> of a good conſcience: But who would venture to <hi>Sea</hi> in a torn, crackt weather-beaten ſhip, having neither <hi>Sails,</hi> nor <hi>Anchor,</hi> nor <hi>ballaſt?</hi> There is no worſe <hi>hell</hi> on earth, then an <hi>ill conſcience,</hi> eſpecially in troublous and <hi>ſuffering</hi> times. Witneſs <hi>Judas, Spira,</hi> &amp;c. It is reported of ſome that have run through all the <hi>Sects</hi> to the very <hi>Ranters,</hi> that they lye under the horrors of hell, roaring and crying, there is no mercy for them: I could wiſh they that firſt <hi>lead</hi> them out of the way might be <hi>ſenſible</hi> of this wrong. Have a care therefore of this <hi>Ship,</hi> that is of ſo great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>paſſenger</hi> or <hi>Pilot</hi> of the ſhip,<note place="margin">3. The worth of the paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the ſoul.</note> is of ſpecial conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to <hi>commend,</hi> yea command, the looking well to the <hi>Ship,</hi> who is either ſav'd or loſt with it; If the <hi>Ship</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize</hi> miſcarry, the <hi>perſon</hi> in it, is in danger of periſhing with them: He that is <hi>careleſs</hi> of a good conſcience, doth not onely looſe his <hi>Merchandize,</hi> the Faith, but <hi>himſelf</hi> alſo, even his own <hi>ſoul;</hi> That's a dreadful place, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 3. <hi>Falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall privily bring in damnable hereſies, denying the Lord that bought them</hi> (as ſome now do) <hi>and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction. Whoſe judgement now of a long time lingreth not and their damnation ſlumbreth not.</hi> In the next verſe to my text, there are a couple of Apoſtates, <hi>Himeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der delivered unto Satan,</hi> by a cenſure of excommunication, that they might <hi>learn not to blaſpheme.</hi> The Church for want of a ſettled government, hath not now this power, but <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:40475:19"/> does it, <hi>immediately</hi> or mediately; mediately by ſome <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of Satan. It's reported, and by ſome confeſſed, that by <hi>ſorceries</hi> and potions, and ſuch like <hi>Satan</hi> hath really and actually had <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of them; immediately God does it, by giving men up to their <hi>own luſts;</hi> which is worſe then if delivered into the actual poſſeſſion of <hi>Satan.</hi> That place ſpeaks the very terrors of hell, to men that have <hi>put away a good conſcience,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they received not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved; for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them strong deluſion, that they ſhould believe a lye, that all they might be damned, who believed not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi> Therefore for the <hi>paſſengers</hi> ſake, your own ſouls ſake, look well to the <hi>ſhip</hi> to keep a good <hi>conſcience,</hi> loſe one, and loſe both.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. The ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note>4. The ſad and lamentable examples of <hi>ſhipwracks,</hi> that are before our eyes, and upon record; <hi>goodly ſhips</hi> and richly laden, that have miſcarryed in ſight of the <hi>Haven.</hi> Here are two in the next verſe, of whom is <hi>Himeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>Philetus</hi> and <hi>Demas,</hi> cap. 4.10. anciently, and <hi>thouſands</hi> more upon our own <hi>ſhore,</hi> lye wreckt and broken to pieces: who have not onely <hi>ſplit</hi> the ſhip, a good <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> but made <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> of the Faith, and are themſelves <hi>drowning</hi> in the <hi>Sea</hi> of perdition, if God be not the more merciful to them. Let theſe be as ſo many <hi>Seamarks</hi> to us all, to cry, <hi>Hold faith,</hi> and above all, if you will hold the <hi>Faith,</hi> get, and keep a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> But ſome concern</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. To the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God.</note>2. The <hi>Miniſters</hi> of God, who repreſent and ſucceed <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> in his office, as <hi>Pilots</hi> of the Church. It concerns them above others, to <hi>hold Faith</hi> and <hi>a good conſcience together;</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to hold the <hi>latter,</hi> if they intend to hold the <hi>former.</hi> I ſhall propound but theſe conſiderations, to perſwade to it, very briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. The heart is very deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</note>1. How eaſie a thing it is, for our hearts to <hi>deceive</hi> us, if not diligently examined and obſerved: we may ſtrongly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve we have a <hi>good conſcience</hi> when it is clean otherwiſe. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſometimes was cheated by his own heart, <hi>I verily thought with my ſelf, that I ought to do many things, contrary
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40475:19"/> to the Name of Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> Act. 26.9. He thought it <hi>conſcience,</hi> but it was <hi>perſecution:</hi> His <hi>conſcience</hi> was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead to maintain his <hi>old way,</hi> with perſecution of the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Goſpel. <hi>There is a way</hi> (ſayes <hi>Solomon) that ſeems right unto a man, but the end thereof are the wayes of death,</hi> Prov. 16.25. There are many wayes, which may ſeem to us, to be the <hi>wayes</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which are in a more general noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the wayes of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> There may be <hi>coloured cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs</hi> (as the Apoſtle calls it) or ſecret <hi>ambition,</hi> pride,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.5.</note> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity at the <hi>heart,</hi> which may incline the <hi>judgement</hi> to ſome plauſible and advantageous <hi>errors</hi> of the times. Look well there to our <hi>conſciences,</hi> there may lodge in them ſome deceivable <hi>luſt,</hi> which may deceive our <hi>judgement</hi> into error. Mark how <hi>Paul</hi> ſearches and ſifts his heart: <hi>The teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity, and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly wiſdom, but by the grace of God, we have had our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in the world, and more abundantly to you wards,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12. And again <hi>chap.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Having renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, not walking in craftineſs, nor handling the word of God deceitfully, but by manifeſtation of the truth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending our ſelves to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God.</hi> That's one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle gives this charge to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. They by parts and place are able to do much good or hurt.</note> not ſo much as a Chriſtian or private man, as a <hi>preacher</hi> of the Goſpel; his <hi>place</hi> and parts called for more <hi>vigilance,</hi> to get and keep a <hi>good conſcience.</hi> Great parts of <hi>learning</hi> and <hi>eminence</hi> of place (as a <hi>leader</hi> in warfare, or a <hi>Pilot</hi> in Seafare) if the heart be unſound, may enable men to do the more hurt, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating, by defending and <hi>colouring</hi> over errors with a ſhew of truth. The greateſt <hi>Hereticks</hi> have been very <hi>learned,</hi> ſubtile men; able to <hi>diſpute</hi> their errors, and ſo to ſubvert the <hi>Faith</hi> of others. So we noted above, That the <hi>Heterodox Teachers,</hi> were acute <hi>diſputers,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.4, 5. And elſewhere he ſayes, <hi>As</hi> Jannes <hi>and</hi> Jambres <hi>withſtood</hi> Moſes (by their inchantments, imitating the miracles of <hi>Moſes) ſo do theſe (ſeducers) reſiſt the truth, men of corupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.8. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> by the opinion of his <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>greatneſs,</hi> drew multitudes of people after him, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.9, 10.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40475:20"/> Hence the Apoſtle gives that caution, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Beware leaſt any man ſpoil you, through Philoſophy and vain deceit, after the traditions of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, if bad anderring, may carry ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with them to hell.</note>3. <hi>Miniſters</hi> of all others, had need to look to their <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>heads,</hi> becauſe if they <hi>miſlead themſelves,</hi> they are able by their <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>favour</hi> with the people) to miſlead many with them into hell. They are called <hi>Guides, Leaders, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots</hi> (as we ſaid at firſt) if thoſe miſcarry, they carry with them thouſands into deſtruction. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> made many <hi>proſelytes,</hi> making them two fold more the children of hell, then themſelves. Thoſe two men named after the text, <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> as alſo <hi>Philetus,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.17, 18. who had made <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> of the Faith, <hi>Their word did eat like a canker, ſaying, that the reſurrection was paſt already and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrew the faith of ſome.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Cretian</hi> ſeducers, <hi>ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whole houſes,</hi> Tit. 1.11. The venerable eſteem of many ſeeming Saint like <hi>Hereticks</hi> of old, carryed many thouſands with them into <hi>Hereſie.</hi> And ſo they do now, their <hi>followers</hi> having their perſons in <hi>admiration</hi> for their <hi>ſeeming holineſs,</hi> have gone after them blindfold, as not thinking it poſſible, that ſuch pious men coul <hi>err,</hi> or <hi>lead</hi> others into errors. <hi>The leaders of my people cauſe them to err, and they that are lead of them are deſtroyed,</hi> was once a <hi>complaint,</hi> and may be our <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The words are rendred by <hi>Tremelius,</hi> thus, <hi>Doctores populi mei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>ſunt ſeductores, The leaders of my people are ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers;</hi> But in the Original, the words are more emphatical, <hi>They that bleſs my people are ſeducers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Iſa. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>and they that are bleſſed by them, are deſtroyed.</hi> They by their <hi>flatteries</hi> pronounced the people <hi>bleſſed</hi> in their <hi>erroneous</hi> and deſtroying wayes; notwithſtanding the <hi>threats</hi> of ruin to them, by the <hi>true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> of God; and when they thought themſelves <hi>bleſſed,</hi> in a bleſſed ſtate, they and their Prophets were <hi>ſwallowed</hi> up in a common deſtruction. Wo to the <hi>ſeduced,</hi> but tiwice and twenty times wo to the <hi>ſeducer;</hi> he that brings in <hi>damnable errors</hi> to deceive and deſtroy others, he brings upon himſelf ſwift deſtruction. His <hi>fire</hi> ſhall be ſo much <hi>hotter</hi> in hell, as he hath more <hi>diſciples</hi> after him, as ſo many <hi>faggots</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the flame. Let <hi>Miniſters</hi> then look well to the <hi>Faith,</hi> to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40475:20"/> keep it ſound, and if they will keep and hold the <hi>Faith,</hi> above <hi>all keepings,</hi> keep a <hi>good conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A word of direction to all, and I have done;<note place="margin">3. Directions to preſerve from this ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack.</note> How we may <hi>preſerve</hi> our ſelves from the <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> of the times, and prevent this common <hi>ſhipwrack</hi> of the <hi>Faith.</hi> There are (as hath been hinted) three things, that do betray men into error, in theſe times, <hi>ignorance, pride,</hi> and <hi>hypocriſie;</hi> the contrary to theſe, are the <hi>preſervatives</hi> of the Faith; <hi>knowledge, humility, ſincerity,</hi> of each a word, and but a word.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Sound and well grounded knowledge</hi> of the truth.<note place="margin">1. A skillful Pilot, ſound knowledge.</note> An ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and unskillful <hi>Pilot</hi> will eaſily endanger the ſhip. You heard before, who they are that are commonly the prey of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, <hi>unlearned and unſtable ſouls,</hi> ſayes Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.16. therefore <hi>unſtable,</hi> becauſe unlearned. They are <hi>children</hi> (ſays <hi>Paul) that are carryed away with every winde of doctrine,</hi> Eph. 4.14. and <hi>ſimple women,</hi> that are led captive by ſeducers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. <hi>untaught, unprincipled</hi> people, never catechized in the fundamentals of Religion. Hence that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly, in all wiſdome,</hi> and Col. 2.2. He prayes for them, that their hearts may be <hi>comforted (or ſtrengthened) unto all riches of the full aſſurance of underſtanding, to the acknowledgement of the myſtery of God, and of the Father, and of Chriſt.</hi> A <hi>ſuperficial,</hi> notional <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> is eaſily ſhaken; it muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>full aſſurance</hi> of underſtanding, that comes to an <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of God, not the <hi>hyſtory</hi> only; an ignorant ſoul among <hi>ſeducers,</hi> is like a <hi>ſhip</hi> at Sea, without a skilfull <hi>Pilote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Knowledge</hi> alone, is not ſufficient, <hi>knowledge puffs up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Store of Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt, true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</note> ſayes the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. But there muſt be the <hi>Grace of Humility</hi> as <hi>ballaſt</hi> to poiſe the ſhip. It's <hi>pride</hi> (you heard) that carries men into error, <hi>pride</hi> of parts, of gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God reſiſts the <hi>proud,</hi> but gives grace to the <hi>humble. The meek will he guid in judgement, the meek will he teach his way,</hi> Pſal. 25.9. It is not more ordinary then juſt with God, to give <hi>proud</hi> men over to their <hi>ſelf-deluſions.</hi> He delights to <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fool</hi> thoſe who are <hi>wiſe</hi> in their own eyes. They ſet their <hi>wiſdom</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods, and he ſets his <hi>wiſdom</hi> againſt them, and <hi>blinds</hi> them with their own wiſdome. Whatever <hi>parts,</hi> or <hi>gifts</hi> or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40475:21"/> 
               <hi>abilites</hi> men have, let them labor the more to be <hi>humble</hi> and lye low. He that in a bluſtring <hi>wind</hi> lyes on the ground, is <hi>ſafe,</hi> whereas he that ſets himſelf upon the <hi>houſe top,</hi> or on a <hi>pinnacle,</hi> is in danger to be <hi>blown down,</hi> and to break his neck. In a word, a man of much <hi>knowledge,</hi> without <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> is like a ſhip at Sea with full ſails, but without <hi>ballaſt;</hi> every <hi>guſt</hi> of wind is ready to <hi>overturn</hi> it, or run it upon a rock.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. A ſtronge Anchor, ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note>3. <hi>Sincerity</hi> is the chief, that <hi>ſecures</hi> all, unrighteouſneſs of heart (thats the <hi>good conſcience</hi> in the text) is like the <hi>Anchor</hi> to a ſhip, that ſtayes it in a ſtorm: So the Pſalmiſt prayed, <hi>Let uprightneſs and integrity preſerve me,</hi> Pſal. 25.21. the reaſon is added; <hi>for I wait on thee.</hi> When the truth is much obſcured by <hi>Hereticks,</hi> that he cannot ſee his way; there's a promiſe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the upright there ariſeth light in the darkneſs,</hi> Pſal. 112.4. God hath promiſed all bleſſings to the upright,<note place="margin">See Pſal. 25.12 Him ſhall he teach in the way that he ſhall chooſe.</note> they are his delight, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.20. <hi>The high way of the upright, is to depart from evil, he that keepeth his way, preſerveth his ſoul,</hi> Prov. 16.17. <hi>He that walketh in his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uprightneſs, feareth the Lord: but he that is perverſe in his wayes, diſpiſeth him,</hi> Prov. 14.2. And how juſt is it with God, to <hi>deſpiſe</hi> that man that <hi>feareth</hi> not God, but is perverſe and <hi>hypocritical</hi> in his wayes: of all men, God hates an <hi>hypocrite,</hi> and will one time or other <hi>uncaſe</hi> him. Hence it is obſervable, that many <hi>weake Chriſtians,</hi> for knowledge, but <hi>ſincere</hi> and upright in heart, perſevere and outſtand all the errors of the times, when many of great <hi>knowledge,</hi> and learning and parts, but open or ſecret <hi>hypocrites,</hi> do <hi>Apoſtate</hi> from the truth. Above all then get a <hi>ſincere</hi> and upright heart, to <hi>walk</hi> up to your knowledge, that will keep both the <hi>Faith,</hi> and your ſelves. I ſhall allude to the Apoſtles words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> ult. There are theſe three <hi>preſervatives</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Faith, <hi>knowledge, humility, ſincerity,</hi> but the chiefeſt of theſe is <hi>ſincerity.</hi> This is that <hi>good conſcience,</hi> in the text, made <hi>good</hi> by ſound and ſaving <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> much bettered by <hi>humility,</hi> and preſerved in both thoſe by <hi>ſincerity.</hi> Let it be it every one of our prayer, <hi>Oh let my heart be ſound in thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, that I be not aſhamed,</hi> Pſal. 119. verſ. 80. And <hi>Oh that my wayes were directed to keep thy Statutes: then ſhall! not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect unto all thy Commandements,</hi> verſ. 5, 6. And I ſhall conclude with my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er too; <hi>Do good, O Lord, to thoſe that are good, and to them that are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in their hearts. As for ſuch as turn aſide unto their crooked wayes, the Lord will lead them forth with the workers of iniquity, but peace ſhall be upon Iſrael.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40475:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
